You had another daughter.
Tenías otra hija, ¿no es cierto?
Where is Ericht Samaya now?
¿Dónde está Ericht Samaya ahora?
She's there.
Está…
Right at Suletta's side.
al lado de Suletta.
Beyond the data storm...
Nos espera al otro lado de la tormenta de datos.
It can't be...
No…
you turned a human into a mobile suit...
¿Una persona en un Mobile Suit?
I want to rewrite the world.
Quiero reescribir el mundo.
So that Eri can be happy.
Para que Eri sea feliz.
I couldn't believe my eyes at first.
Al principio no podía creerlo.
Eri's biometric code was completely synched with the data storm.
El código biométrico de Eri estaba sincronizado con la tormenta de datos.
Even so...
Aun así,
her child's body couldn't endure the harshness of outer space.
su cuerpo infantil no podía soportar la dureza del espacio exterior.
I decided to use Lfrith to keep Eri alive.
Decidí usar el Lfrith para mantener viva a Eri.
Alive as Aerial.
Viva como el Aerial.
You used the data storm's network to transfer her biometric code, is that it?
¿Usaste la red de la tormenta de datos para transferir su código biométrico?
Eri is nothing more than Permet particles now.
Eri ahora mismo no es más que partículas Permet.
Without Aerial as her body, she'd disintegrate in physical space.
Sin el Aerial como su cuerpo, se desintegraría en el espacio físico.
But with a Permet score of eight...
Pero con una puntuación Permet de ocho…
If we can expand the range of the data storm through Quiet Zero...
Si podemos ampliar la tormenta de datos usando Quiet Zero…
Then Eri...
¡Entonces, Eri podrá vivir en libertad!
Won't you help me?
¿No quieres ayudarme,
Bel?
Bel?
I can't.
No puedo.
Oh?
Vaya. ¿Por qué?
These aren't the principles of the Vanadis Institute.
Esos no son los principios del Instituto Vanadis.
But didn't you make enhanced humans?
¿Ustedes no seguían la Teoría de la Expansión Neural
Using an artificial central nervous system with resistance to the data storm.
y creaban humanos mejorados con un sistema nervioso central artificial?
Dr. Cardo refused to accept it.
El doctor Cardo se negó a aceptarla.
Don't...
No…
The one who conceived the idea...
-Y esa idea la concebiste tú, ¿no? -¡Detente!
Say no more...
No digas más…
Please.
Por favor.
There will be no escape...
Tampoco habrá escapatoria
for you, either.
para ti.
The terrorist attack at the Asticassia School of Technology
El atentado sufrido en la Escuela Tecnológica Asticassia
has now, with the kidnapping of Grassley's Sarius Zenelli...
resultó en el secuestro de Sarius Zenelli, de Grassley.
The group claiming responsibility, the Dawn of Fold,
ALBA DE FOLD SE DECLARAN RESPONSABLES
is also said to be involved in the recent accident at Plant Quetta...
también estaban involucrados en el accidente de la Planta Quetta.
Jeturk CEO Vim Jeturk has been reported dead.
Vim Jeturk, el CEO de Jeturk, falleció.
According to some sources, the Group's President, Delling Rembran, is injured as well.
Y según algunas fuentes, el presidente Delling Rembran está herido.
With the Benerit Group carrying out security operations at its own discretion
Con el Benerit Group llevando a cabo operaciones de seguridad por su cuenta,
growing anti-Spacian sentiment on Earth has escalated many protests into riots.
el creciente sentimiento anti-Spacian desencadenó revueltas.
The Group has been heavily criticized for its recent actions
El grupo fue criticado duramente por sus actos y se cree que…
It seems our confidential matters have been leaked.
Parece que se filtraron nuestros asuntos confidenciales.
Any clue where Sarius Zenelli is?
¿Se sabe algo del paradero de Sarius Zenelli?
Nothing but the single video message he sent.
Nada más que el mensaje por video que envió.
The front management company is continuing the search.
La administración sigue buscándolo.
What is Cathedra doing?
¿Qué hace Cathedra?
After two attacks, they still can't catch them?
¿Aún no los atrapan luego de dos ataques?
Weren't you also there during the Open Campus incident?
¿Tú no estabas presente en el incidente de las puertas abiertas?
All these hardline policies have backfired.
Esas políticas tan firmes no funcionaron.
The Space Assembly League is starting to dig around too.
La Unión del Congreso Espacial comenzó a investigar.
At this rate...
A este paso…
Yes.
Sí.
We'll have no choice but to elect a new president.
Habremos de elegir a un nuevo presidente.
It's just as we predicted.
Es como se predijo.
You'll run in the election, right?
Te presentarás, ¿verdad?
I don't intend to miss this chance.
No quiero desaprovechar la ocasión.
Isn't Miss Miorine going to take over for President Delling?
¿Miorine no asumirá el puesto del presidente Delling?
Blood alone isn't enough to put you at the top.
La sangre no basta para llevarte a la cima.
Let's see. If she had backing from one of the three branches,
Veamos… Si tuviera el apoyo de una de las tres ramas,
she could--
-tal vez… -Shaddiq.
I won't try to be her partner anymore. I'm going to the head office.
Dejaré de intentar ser su compañero. Voy a la oficina central.
Everyone's waiting.
Están esperando todos.
So GUND-ARM, Inc. has been cleared of suspicion?
¿La S. p. A. GUND-ARM está libre de sospecha?
We've found no evidence of your involvement, that's all.
No tenemos pruebas de que estuvieran involucrados.
I see. Too bad for you.
Ya veo. Qué mal, ¿verdad?
We're going to choose a new president.
Elegiremos a un nuevo presidente.
You should be happy.
Alégrate.
Now you won't be a trophy in the dueling game.
Ya no serás un trofeo en los duelos.
I couldn't care less...
Todo eso…
about all of that.
no me importa.
Episode 16
Episodio 16 El ciclo de las ofensas
The front is currently under a state of emergency.
El frente se encuentra en un estado de emergencia.
In accordance with school emergency regulations,
Según las normas escolares,
all students are currently subject to activity restrictions.
los alumnos tienen restringidas ciertas actividades.
There are fewer students.
Hay menos estudiantes.
Can't blame those who left.
No puedo culpar a los que se fueron.
My parents are picking me up next week.
Mis padres vendrán por mí la próxima semana.
Aren't you taking time off school, Rouji?
No necesitamos Earthians en Asticassia
What about you, Secelia?
¿Y tú, Secelia?
If I leave too, no one can hold any duels.
Si me marcho, nadie podrá hacer duelos.
So you do have a sense of duty.
Así que tienes sentido del deber.
It's almost the Princess's birthday, right?
Dentro de poco será el cumpleaños de la princesa, ¿no?
At least I should be here to see who becomes her groom.
Al menos debería estar aquí para ver quién es su novio.
Out of the way, Suletta!
¡Aparta, Suletta!
Just how long do they have to keep Nika in custody?!
¿Hasta cuándo tendrán encerrada a Nika?
You can't take that wrench!
¡Suelta la llave inglesa!
We're all suspended already.
Ya nos impusieron una suspensión.
Don't cause any more trouble.
No causes más problemas.
Didn't they say they're still investigating?
-¿No seguían investigando? -¡Ya hace cinco días!
They're always suspicious of us Earthians, that's all.
Solo sospechan de los Earthians, eso es todo.
Yeah, but even so,
Sí, pero aun así,
why'd they have to confiscate Aerial and my own Demi too?
¿por qué tenían que confiscar el Aerial y mi Demi?
Suletta's putting up with it, isn't she?
Suletta está resistiendo, ¿no?
Just two more days and our suspension--
Solo dos días más, y la suspensión…
You jerks...
Desgraciados…
What are you doing?
¿Qué hacen?
Get out, terrorists!
¡Fuera de aquí, terroristas!
You guys brought the Gundams that attacked us, didn't you?
¡Ustedes trajeron a los Gundams que nos atacaron!
Get real!
¡Eso no es así!
None of us knew anything about Sophie and the other girl!
Nosotros no sabíamos nada de Sophie y la otra chica.
So quit harassing us, will you?!
Dejen de hostigarnos, por favor.
You're protecting your fellow witches.
Así que protegen a las brujas.
Witches?
¿Brujas?
Our company staff said so.
En nuestra empresa se dice eso.
The witches who made the Gundams took pilots' lives with their experiments.
Las brujas que crearon los Gundams mataron a los pilotos experimentando.
O-Our Gundam isn't like that--
Nuestro Gundam no es así…
You took lives too! In the Rumble Ring!
Pero ¡mataron en el Rumble Ring!
Jubeju was... a precious friend to us!
¡Jubeju era muy importante para nosotros!
But you...
Pero tú…
Give us back Jubeju!
¡Regrésennos a Jubeju!
Murderers!
¡Asesinos!
Martin...
-¡Martin!
You creeps are gonna pay for that!
¡Esto lo pagarán caro!
Stop it, all of you!
Paren de una vez.
Ms... Miorine?
¿Miorine?
I don't think the school will ignore direct evidence of assault.
Dudo que la escuela ignore las pruebas de la agresión.
Thank you very much... for treating my injuries.
Gracias por tratar mis heridas.
Nika Nanaura.
Nika Nanaura.
Don't you want to join our group?
¿No quieres unirte a nuestro grupo?
I've been watching you.
Te estuve observando.
Your skill as a mechanic, and your behavior on campus...
Tu habilidad como mecánica, tu comportamiento en el campus…
If you're with us, you can continue your studies elsewhere.
Si estás con nosotros, podrás seguir tus estudios donde sea.
You could even achieve your dream of bridging Earth and Space.
Podrías cumplir tu sueño de ser el puente entre Tierra y espacio.
I've made a decision.
Ya lo decidí.
I shouldn't act like a victim anymore.
Dejaré de comportarme como una víctima.
Even if the ends are just, I don't want to use the wrong means.
Aunque el fin lo justifique, no usaré todos los medios.
Even if it's for Earth's sake?
¿Ni por la Tierra?
Are you an Earthian too?
¿Tú también eres una Earthian?
I was until Grassley took me in.
Lo era hasta que me acogió Grassley.
Ideals alone can't change reality
Los ideales no pueden cambiar la realidad.
You can't leave here either.
No puedes salir de aquí.
But Shaddiq and I will make it happen.
Pero Shaddiq y yo lo haremos.
The dream of bridging Earth and Space...
El sueño de ser el puente entre Tierra y espacio…
I'll cut right to the chase.
Iré al grano.
Obtain the Aerial for us.
Consíguenos el Aerial.
And what about winning over Suletta Mercury?
¿Y qué hay de vencer a Suletta Mercury?
The presidential race is beginning.
La campaña electoral está por comenzar.
The dueling game is over.
Se acabaron los duelos.
Plus...
Además, tu falta de motivación peleando durante el Rumble Ring
has left us rather disappointed.
nos decepcionó mucho.
I was merely observing the situation.
Solo observaba la situación.
The Aerial has been temporarily confiscated because of the recent incident.
Confiscaron temporalmente el Aerial debido al incidente.
If you want to live, carry out your mission at all costs.
Si quieres vivir, cumple la misión a como dé lugar.
Benerit Group Front
Frente del Benerit Group
What's the latest?
¿Situación?
The company has split into six factions.
La compañía se dividió en seis facciones.
We're in sixth place?
¿Estamos en sexto lugar?
We'll be number one soon enough.
Pronto seremos los primeros.
That's the plan.
Esa es la idea.
It feels like...
Es como si llevara fuera una eternidad.
Lauda, Petra...
Lauda, Petra…
How've you been?
¿Qué tal todo?
Mr. Guel?
¿Guel?
Brother! Brother, you're...
¡Guel! Guel, re…
Mr. Lauda!
-¡Lauda!
I think he's just relieved.
Creo que es por el alivio.
After you disappeared, Mr. Guel, and then that terrible event happened...
Tras tu desaparición y aquel terrible acontecimiento,
Mr. Lauda suddenly had to take over the company.
Lauda se vio obligado a tomar el control de la empresa.
The Group has kept pressing him to give explanations, take responsibility...
El grupo lo presionó para que dé explicaciones
Oh... forgive me.
Ah, perdona.
Your father...
Tu padre…
Yeah. I'm aware.
Sí. Soy consciente de ello.
Mr. Lauda didn't even have time to grieve.
Lauda no tuvo tiempo ni para llorar.
He's been struggling all alone.
Estuvo luchando él solo.
That's why...
Y por eso…
Petra.
Petra.
Take care of Lauda.
Cuida de Lauda.
I'll handle the rest.
Yo me ocupo del resto.
Mr. Guel!
¡Guel!
Welcome back.
Bienvenido.
What do you mean?
¿Cómo dices?
Nika Nanaura was taken by other parties disguised as front management employees.
Otro grupo se llevó a Nika Nanaura camuflándola como una empleada.
Can you confirm the departure list?
¿Puedes confirmar la lista de salidas?
Of course!
Por supuesto.
But in return, will you grant me a favor?
Pero ¿me harías un favor a cambio?
I'd like a pass to freely enter and exit GUND-ARM, Inc.
Quiero un pase para entrar y salir de la S. p. A GUND-ARM.
You want to investigate our company too?
¿Quieres investigar nuestra compañía?
I'm curious about the Shin Sei Development Corporation you acquired.
Me intriga mucho la compañía de Desarrollo Shin Sei que adquiriste.
If you inform me of what you find...
Si me reportas lo que descubras…
You're going directly?
¿Irás en persona?
The costs for their Gundam repair were excessive,
El precio de la reparación de su Gundam fue enorme
and a lot of equipment was sent to Plant Quetta...
y se envió mucho equipo a la Planta Quetta.
Is that appropriate for a bottom-ranked company?
¿Es apropiado para una empresa bajo mínimos?
Is the Group behind this?
¿El grupo está detrás de esto?
Even if it requires groundless accusations,
Aunque necesiten acusaciones sin fundamento,
the higher-ups plan to forcibly intervene in the Benerit Group.
los de arriba quieren intervenir en el Benerit Group.
We have to prevent unnecessary fuss.
Debemos evitar problemas innecesarios.
It's our role as mediators.
Es nuestra labor como mediadores.
What did you find out?
¿Qué descubriste?
Nika isn't with the front management company.
Nika no está en la administración.
So where is she, then?
¿Y dónde está entonces?
They're looking into it for me.
Lo están comprobando por mí.
Wait until I hear back.
Les informaré.
But--
-Pero… -Entendido.
We couldn't find out anything on our own.
Nosotros no pudimos descubrir nada.
So... you know...
Así que…
Thanks.
Gracias.
You're welcome.
De nada.
Meanwhile, here you are.
Y de paso, toma esto.
The company's suspended from doing business,
La empresa tiene prohibida la actividad,
but we're still incurring maintenance costs.
pero seguimos teniendo gastos.
Please authorize these payments as well.
Por favor, autoriza estos pagos.
And please look over these notifications!
Y mira estas notificaciones.
I'd like to buy a new app.
Quiero comprar una app nueva.
I...I, uh...
Yo… Este…
Over here!
Miren.
Uh, well, I...
Ah, este…
I'd like you... to look...
Me gustaría que vieras el invernadero.
Lilique! Organize the materials for me to check.
Lilique, organiza los materiales para revisarlos.
Right!
Bien.
Aren't you coming?
¿No vendrás?
Y-Yes!
¡Sí!
Hello!
¡Hola!
Is there anyone home?
¿Hay alguien?
Who's that?
-¿Quién es? -¿Mamá?
"Mom"?!
¿"Mamá"?
What are you doing here?
¿A qué viniste?
The investigators finished questioning me.
Los investigadores ya dejaron de interrogarme.
I hadn't seen you at all since the incident, right?
No te veía desde el incidente, ¿no?
I see. I'll show you around, then.
Ya veo. Te mostraré todo esto.
Don't worry. I can get around by myself.
Tranquila. Puedo hacerlo sola.
But...
Pero…
You're going out with Ms. Miorine, right?
Te irás con Miorine, ¿no?
You should look after your bride.
Deberías cuidar de tu novia.
Yeah! You're right!
Sí, es verdad.
Let's go.
-Vamos. -Bien.
We'll be back!
Nos vemos.
Have fun!
Pásenla bien.
How nice to meet you all. I'm Suletta's mother.
Mucho gusto en conocerlos. Soy la madre de Suletta.
Sorry about this, Suletta Mercury...
Lo siento, Suletta Mercury.
But I'm stealing your family member.
Pero te robaré a tu familiar.
No response...
No hay respuesta.
Wasn't Number Four able to use it?
¿No pudo usarlo el número cuatro?
A data storm...
Una tormenta de datos…
Why, all of a sudden...
¿Por qué ahora?
Stay away.
Aléjate.
Suletta...
¿Suletta…
Mercury?
Mercury?
You can't come here.
No puedes venir aquí.
No...
No…
Who are you people?
¿Quiénes son?
What the heck... is this Gundam?
¿Qué rayos es este Gundam?
This isn't like the Pharact at all!
¡No es para nada como el Pharact!
You're unable to handle it.
No puedes controlarlo.
This is an order from above.
Es una orden de arriba.
You should help, too.
Deberías ayudar.
I can't.
No puedo.
It must be easier tinkering with this than with enhanced humans.
Ha de ser más fácil jugar con esto que con los humanos mejorados.
What should I have done instead?
¿Qué debería haber hecho?
After my colleagues and research went up in flames,
Cuando mis compañeros y mi investigación se perdieron,
I had to take refuge on Peil's payroll.
acabé trabajando para la gente de Peil.
But one day... GUND's ideals would lead to a better future--
Pero un día… Los ideales de GUND llevarán a un futuro mejor…
Even for human experiments like me?
¿Incluso para experimentos como yo?
You don't want to die yourself,
No quieres morir por ti,
but you don't give a damn about my future!
pero mi futuro no te importa.
You're wrong, I--
-No, yo… -¡No me repliques!
I'm going to report you to the higher-ups.
Pienso informar a los jefes.
I did as you said
Hice lo que me dijiste
and used the Andes model.
-y usé el modelo Andes. -Sí.
Did you get my emails?
¿Recibiste mis correos?
I did. Three a day.
Sí. Tres al día.
And I haven't lost any duels.
Y no perdí ningún duelo.
I can tell from your uniform.
Eso me dice tu uniforme.
Are you mad at me, Ms. Miorine?
¿Estás enojada conmigo?
About what happened at the plant...
Por lo que pasó en la planta…
No, you should be mad at me.
No, deberías estar enojada tú conmigo.
You saved my life and my father's.
Nos salvaste la vida a mi padre y a mí.
And yet, I said something awful to you.
Pero te dije algo terrible.
I wanted to say I was sorry...
Solo quería disculparme contigo.
I should have thanked you.
Debí haberte agradecido.
I knew it.
Lo sabía. Es como me dijo mi madre.
She told me that you'd understand eventually.
Me dijo que acabarías entendiéndolo.
That Aerial and I did the right thing.
Entenderías que el Aerial y yo hicimos lo correcto.
The right thing?
¿Lo correcto?
Yes! Run and gain one. Move forward and gain two!
Sí. Si huyes, ganas uno. Si avanzas, ganas dos.
Because I fought without running away,
Como luché sin huir,
I was able to protect you and all of Earth House!
pude protegerte a ti y la residencia terrícola.
How can you smile like that?
¿Cómo puedes sonreír así?
I know you rescued me.
Sé que me rescataste.
But... you smashed...
Pero machacaste…
smashed another person to death...
Machacaste a otra persona.
I can't smile!
¡Yo no puedo sonreír!
Right thing or not, you shouldn't smile about it!
¡Ya fuera lo correcto o no, no sonrías por eso!
What? B-But only the two of us could save everyone.
¿Qué? Pero solo nosotras dos pudimos salvar a todos.
Is that what your mom told you?
¿Eso es lo que te dijo tu madre?
Yes.
Sí.
Will you do anything your mom tells you to?
¿Harás todo lo que te diga tu madre?
I wouldn't say "anything"...
Yo no diría "todo"…
What if she told you to give up your dream of building a school at Mercury?
¿Y si te dijera que te olvidaras de crear una escuela en Mercurio?
I'd be troubled... I guess...
Pues supongo que sería un problema…
But...
Pero…
But if my mom told me to, I'd give up.
Pero si me lo dijera mi madre, lo abandonaría.
GUND-ARM, Inc. isn't a tool of war!
¡La S. p. A GUND-ARM no es una herramienta de guerra!
Didn't we all decide we'd build Gundams that can save lives through medicine?!
¿No decidimos que haríamos Gundams que salvaran vidas mediante la medicina?
If your mother told you to, would you use Gundams to kill people?
Si te lo dijera tu madre, ¿los usarías para matar a gente?
Yes.
Sí.
If Mom told me to.
Si me lo dijera ella, sí.
It's because I did what Mom said, that I got to go to school.
Pude venir a la escuela porque hice lo que me decía.
And make friends.
E hice amigos.
And meet you, Ms. Miorine...
Y te conocí a ti.
So I know my mom is always right.
Así que sé que mi madre siempre tiene razón.
Ms. Miorine?
¿Miorine?
Just a little longer...
Solo un poco más…
Wait for me, Eri.
Espérame, Eri.
Prospera!
¡Prospera!
What are you planning to do with Suletta?
¿Qué piensas hacer con Suletta?
She's a good little girl, isn't she?
Es muy buena chica, ¿verdad?
This isn't funny!
¡No fastidies!
That girl will do anything you tell her to!
¡Esa chica hará todo lo que le digas!
I won't let you have your way with her anymore!
¡No dejaré que sigas manipulándola así!
And what then?
¿Y qué?
Do you want to have your way with her next?
¿Ahora quieres ser tú la que la manipule?
Just like your father...
Como tu padre…
You're the one using her as a puppet!
¡La estás usando como tu marioneta!
My lousy father has nothing to do with this!
-¡Mi padre no tiene relación! -Ya te digo yo que sí.
Because your father is the object of my family's vengeance.
Porque tu padre es el objetivo de la venganza de mi familia.
I guess that man Rajan kept his mouth shut.
Parece que Rajan cerró bien la boca.
Wait a second...
Espera… ¿Qué di…?
I meant exactly what I said.
Lo que oíste.
During the Vanadis Incident 21 years ago,
Durante el Incidente de Vanadis de hace 21 años,
Delling Rembran deprived me of my husband, my colleagues...
Delling Rembran me privó de mi marido, mis compañeros…
and my mentor.
y mi mentora.
In the name of "witch-hunting," that man slaughtered everyone at the Institute.
En nombre de la caza de brujas, ese tipo mató a la gente del Instituto.
We're the only ones who survived.
Solo sobrevivimos nosotras.
You're lying...
Es mentira…
You accused Suletta of being a murderer,
Acusaste a Suletta de ser una asesina,
but you're in the same position.
pero tú estás en la misma posición.
Inside the circle of murderers...
En la del ciclo de los asesinos…
I want you to hear them too.
Quiero que los oigas.
The screams and cries of my comrades...
Los chillidos y los gritos de mis compañeros.
"Avenge our deaths... Kill that man Delling..."
"Venga nuestras muertes. Mata a Delling".
They're whispering it in my ear, even as we speak.
Me lo susurran al oído en este mismo instante.
If you want revenge, why don't you adults kill each other?
Si quieres venganza, ¿por qué no se matan los adultos?
But leave Suletta out of your vengeance!
Pero ¡deja a Suletta al margen de tu venganza!
You're quite an admirable bride.
Eres una novia admirable.
Will you cooperate with me, then?
¿Cooperarás conmigo?
Quiet Zero...
Quiet Zero…
At this rate, there'll be a new president, and our plan will be ruined.
A este paso habrá un presidente nuevo y el plan se desmoronará.
That's why, Miorine Rembran...
Y por eso, Miorine Rembran,
you must become the next president.
debes ser la próxima presidenta.
Me?
¿Yo?
I could never...
Yo no podría…
You can do it.
Obvio que puedes.
After all, you're Delling Rembran's
Puesto que eres la hija de Delling Rembran
blood-stained daughter.
con las manos manchadas de sangre.
Next time on Mobile Suit Gundam the Witch from Mercury,
Próximamente: "Cosas importantes".
Episode 17
Episodio 17 Cosas importantes
Illustration: Kei Mochizuki
Ilustración: Kei Mochizuki